3-42, Athabasca Hall, Edmonton, Alberta, T6G 2E8, Canada

■ karim.ali@ualberta.ca | A karimali.ca | karimhamdanali | M @karimhamdanali

Research Areas

My primary research interest is to develop and evaluate various program analysis techniques that can be used in practice by exploring three aspects: scalability, precision, and usability. My interests span programming languages and software systems.

Education

Ph.D., Computer Science 2014

UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA

- · Advisor: Ondřei Lhoták
- Thesis: The Separate Compilation Assumption
- · Committee: Jan Vitek, Frank Tip, Reid Holmes, and Werner Dietl

MMath, Computer Science 2010

University of Waterloo, Canada

- · Advisor: Raouf Boutaba
- Thesis: Algorizmi A Configurable Virtual Testbed to Generate Datasets for Offline Evaluation of Intrusion Detection Systems
- Reviewers: Ian MacKillop and Urs Hengartner

B.Sc., Computer Science 2007

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

- · Advisors: Sherif G. Aly and Sherif El-Kassas
- Thesis: A Jabber Framework for Building Communication Capable Java Mobile Applications
- · Minor: Mathematics

Professional Experience

Assistant Professor, Department of Computing Science

University of Alberta, Canada

Research Assistant Professor, Department of Computing Science

University of Alberta, Canada

Postdoctoral Researcher, Secure Software Engineering

TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY

- Designing novel static analyses to detect misuses of cryptographic APIs in software systems
- · Exploring new static analysis techniques that incorporate user feedback in a just-in-time fashion
- Developing various extensions to the IFDS analysis framework

Graduate Research Assistant, Programming Languages Group

UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA

• Conducted research for constructing partial static call graphs for Java programs

- Developed various call graph construction algorithms for Scala
- Studied static analysis techniques for various JVM-hosted languages

Graduate Research Assistant, Network Security Research Group

UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA

- · Worked on various models of Intrusion Detection Systems: e.g., peer-to-peer, kernel methods
- Developed Algorizmi, an open-source evaluation system for Intrusion Detection Systems

Researcher, Department of Computer Science

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT · Studied new techniques to support location management in Java-based pervasive systems

KARIM ALI · CURRICULUM VITAE 1/5 DECEMBER 1, 2017

2008-2009

2007

2010-2014

Jul 2017-Present

Jul 2016-Jul 2017

Oct 2014-Jul 2016

ITWORX, EGYPT

· Redesigned the graphical user interface of the stock brokerage system for Execution Ltd., London, UK

Awards and Honors ___

ACM SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper Award

2017

INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM ON SOFTWARE TESTING AND ANALYSIS

Distinguished Artifact Award

2014

2012-2014

\$20,000

EUROPEAN CONFERENCE ON OBJECT-ORIENTED PROGRAMMING

David R. Cheriton Scholarship
UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA

Special Graduate Scholarship
University of Waterloo, Canada \$2,500

Queen Elizabeth II Graduate Scholarship in Science and Technology2012CANADA\$5,000

Special Graduate Scholarship2011UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA\$1,000

Graduate Entrance Scholarship
UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA
\$3,000

B.Sc. Summa Cum Laude Honors 2007

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

Best CS Group Graduation Project Award

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

Shell Endowed Scholarship

The American University in Cairo, Egypt 30% off tuition

Professional Service _

PROGRAM COMMITTEE ORGANIZATION

SPLASH-I Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Humanity (SPLASH) 2018
SPLASH-I Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Humanity (SPLASH) 2017
Artifact Evaluation Co-Chair, International Symposium on Engineering Secure Software and Systems (ESSoS)

Demonstration Track Co-Chair, ACM SIGSOFT Symposium on the Foundations of Software Engineering (FSE)

2017

Program Committee Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN International Workshop on the State Of the Art in Program Analysis (SOAP) @ PLDI 2017

PROGRAM COMMITTEE MEMBER

ECOOP, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming2018ISSTA, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis2018CASCON, International Conference on Computer Science and Software Engineering2017Onward!, ACM International Symposium on New Ideas, New Paradigms, and Reflections on Programming and Software2017

ARTIFACT EVALUATION COMMITTEE MEMBER

ISSTA, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis	2016
PLDI, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation	2015
ECOOP, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming	2015
ECOOP, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming	2014

WORKSHOP ORGANIZATION

WORKSHOP ORGANIZATION	
Co-Organizer, Compiler-Driven Performance Workshop @ CASCON Co-Organizer, WALA Hackathon @ PLDI Co-Organizer, Workshop on Designing Code Analysis Frameworks (DECAF) @ ISSTA Co-Organizer, Workshop on WALA @ PLDI	2017 2017 2016 2015
Reviewer	
SCP, Science of Computer Programming TSE, IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering	2015 2013
OTHER	
Associate Editor, IEEE Software Blog Web Chair, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming (ECOOP) Web Chair, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA) Subreviewer, International Conference on Compiler Construction (CC)	2017–Present 2018 2018 2017
Research Funding	
Scalable and Precise Program Analysis for Modern Software Systems Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) Discovery Grant With: Sole PI Amount: CAD\$125,000	2017–2022
 Improving the Inlining Algorithms in the IBM Just-in-Time (JIT) Compiler IBM Centre for Advanced Studies Research Fellowship With: Sole PI Amount: CAD\$30,000 	2017–2018
 Coarse-Grained Call Graph Analysis of Android Applications Huawei Innovation Research Program (HIRP) With: Sole PI Amount: USD\$46,200 	2017–2018
Publications	
Refereed Journal Articles	
Karim Ali , Marianna Rapoport, Ondřej Lhoták, Julian Dolby, and Frank Tip. "Type-Based Call Graph Construction Algorithms for Scala". <i>ACM Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology</i> , 25(1), 9:1–9:43, 2015.	TOSEM '15
Sherif Aly, Sarah Nadi, and Karim Hamdan . "A Java-Based Programming Language Support of Location Management in Pervasive Systems". <i>International Journal of Computer Science and Network Security</i> , 8(6), pp. 329–336, 2008.	IJCSNS '08
REFEREED CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS	
Stefan Krüger, Sarah Nadi, Michael Reif, Karim Ali , Mira Mezini, Eric Bodden, Florian Göpfert, Felix Günther, Christian Weinert, Daniel Demmler, and Ram Kamath. "CogniCrypt: Supporting Developers in using Cryptography". <i>International Conference on Automated Software Engineering</i> , (to appear), 2017.	ASE '17 Tool Paper
Johannes Späth, Karim Ali , and Eric Bodden. "IDE ^{al} : Efficient and Precise Alias-aware Dataflow Analysis". <i>ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages and Applications</i> , (to appear), 2017.	OOPSLA '17
Taylor Lloyd, Artem Chikin, Erick Ochoa, Karim Ali , and J Nelson Amaral. "A Case for Better Integration of Host and Target Compilation When Using OpenCL for FPGAs". <i>International Workshop on FPGAs for Software Programmers</i> , (to appear), 2017.	FSP '17
Mona Nashaat, Karim Ali , and James Miller. "Detecting Security Vulnerabilities in Object-Oriented PHP Programs". <i>IEEE International Working Conference on Source Code Analysis and Manipulation</i> , (to appear), 2017.	SCAM '17

Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, **Karim Ali**, Ben Livshits, Eric Bodden, Justin Smith, and Emerson Murphy-Hill. "Just-in-Time Static Analysis". *International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis*, pp. 307–317, 2017.

Distinguished Paper

Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, **Karim Ali**, Ben Livshits, Eric Bodden, Justin Smith, and Emerson Murphy-Hill. "Cheetah: Just-in-Time Taint Analysis for Android Apps". *International Conference on Software Engineering - Companion Volume*, pp. 39–42, 2017.

ICSE '17 Tool Paper

ISSTA '17

Johannes Späth, Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, **Karim Ali**, and Eric Bodden. "Boomerang: Demand-Driven Flow-Sensitive, Field-Sensitive, and Context-Sensitive Pointer Analysis". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, 22:1–22:26, 2016.

ECOOP '16

Steven Arzt, Sarah Nadi, **Karim Ali**, Eric Bodden, Sebastian Erdweg, and Mira Mezini. "Towards Secure Integration of Cryptographic Software". *ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on New Ideas in Programming and Reflections on Software at SPLASH*, pp. 1–13, 2015.

Onward! '15

Karim Ali, Marianna Rapoport, Ondřej Lhoták, Julian Dolby, and Frank Tip. "Constructing Call Graphs of Scala Programs". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, pp. 54–79, 2014.

ECOOP '14
Distinguished Artifact

Karim Ali and Ondřej Lhoták. "Averroes: Whole-Program Analysis without the Whole Program". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, pp. 378–400, 2013.

ECOOP '13

Karim Ali and Ondřej Lhoták. "Application-Only Call Graph Construction". *European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming*, pp. 688–712, 2012.

ECOOP '12

OTHER REFEREED PUBLICATIONS

Karim Ali, Issam Aib, and Raouf Boutaba. "P2P-AIS: A P2P Artificial Immune Systems architecture for detecting DDoS flooding attacks". *Global Information Infrastructure Symposium*, 2009.

GIIS '09

Karim Ali and Raouf Boutaba. "Applying Kernel Methods to Anomaly-based Intrusion Detection Systems". *Global Information Infrastructure Symposium*, 2009.

GIIS '09

Selected Invited Talks

"Designing Tomorrow's Static Analyses - Addressing Scalability, Precision, and Usability". University of Colorado Boulder, 2016.

Boulder, CO, USA

RIT '16

SRA '15

"Designing Tomorrow's Static Analyses - Addressing Scalability, Precision, and Usability". Rochester Institute of Technology, 2016.

Rochester, NY, USA

"Designing Tomorrow's Static Analyses - Addressing Scalability, Precision, and Usability". Iowa State University, 2016.

ISU '16 Ames, IA, USA

"Evaluating Call Graph Construction for JVM-hosted Language Implementations". IFIP Working Group 2.4 on Software Implementation Technology, 2015.

IFIP '15 Boppard, Germany

"Averroes - Letting go of the library!" Samsung Research America, 2015.

Mountain View, CA, USA

"Whole-Program Analysis Without the Whole Program". McGill University, 2015.

McGill '15

Montreal, QC, Canada

Students_

CURRENT

Erick OchoaUniversity of Alberta, Canada, (co-supervised with José Nelson Amaral)

2017-Present

Master's

Johannes Späth

2015-Present

University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden)

Ph.D.

Stefan Krüger 2015-Present University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden) Ph.D. Lisa Nguyen 2015-Present University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden) ALUMNI **Manuel Benz** 2016 TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY Ph.D. at University of Paderborn • Master's Thesis: Interprocedural Data Dependency Graphs Michael Appel 2016 TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY · Master's Thesis: Call Graph Summaries for the Android SDK **Stefan Triller** 2015-2016 TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY Software Engineer at Deutsche Telekom · Ph.D. withdrawn **Teaching** INSTRUCTOR CMPUT 620 Static Program Analysis, University of Alberta, Canada Fall 2017 CMPUT 229 Computer Organization and Architecture I, University of Alberta, Canada Winter 2017 CMPUT 620 Static Program Analysis, University of Alberta, Canada Fall 2016 SAS Static Analysis Seminar, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany Winter 2015 Co-Instructor **APSA** Applied Static Analysis, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany Spring 2016 SUBSTITUTE LECTURER **DECA** Designing Code Analyses for Large Software Systems, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany Winter 2014 CS 241 Foundations of Sequential Programs, University of Waterloo, Canada Spring 2013 **GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT** Foundations of Sequential Programs, University of Waterloo, Canada CS 241 2011-2013 CS 444/644 Compiler Construction, University of Waterloo, Canada 2011-2013 Software Design and Architectures, University of Waterloo, Canada CS 446/646 Spring 2011 CS 456/656 Computer Networks, University of Waterloo, Canada 2008-2010 Introduction to Programming Principles, University of Waterloo, Canada CS 125 Winter 2008 Security Engineering, The American University in Cairo, Egypt CS 448 Fall 2007 Undergraduate Teaching Assistant CS 448 Security Engineering, The American University in Cairo, Egypt Fall 2007 CS 330 **Computer Architecture**, The American University in Cairo, Egypt 2005-2006 CS 106 Fundamentals of Computer Science, The American University in Cairo, Egypt 2004-2005 Volunteer Work CyberPatriot Technical Mentor, Strathcona High School, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada 2016-2018 Graduate Student Ambassador, University of Waterloo, Canada Fall 2013 Tour Guide, Computer Science Open House, University of Waterloo, Canada Winter 2012 President, Egyptian Students Association, University of Waterloo, Canada 2010-2011 Ushers Committee Leader, Honors Assembly, The American University in Cairo, Egypt

Academic Committee Head, ACM Chapter, The American University in Cairo, Egypt

Spring 2007

Spring 2007